<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Dingmaotu Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-19T17:42:39+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://dingmaotu.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ding Li]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[iamliding@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Compiling Emacs 24.3 on Windows]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2013/03/12/compiling-emacs-24-dot-3-on-windows/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-12T11:42:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2013/03/12/compiling-emacs-24-dot-3-on-windows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Emacs 24.3, a new release, has come out! The official win32 build however has
not. So we are gonna do it by ourselves. Building Emacs on windows is not that
hard, but you must be careful about choosing the correct tools, or your
building experience will be full of bumps.</p>

<p>If I am going to build a project on Windows, I will consider using a free
version of Visual C++. But for Emacs, the support for VC is very poor! You are
not going to succeed with it. Maybe there are few Emacs developers interested
in M$ products, I definitely want Emacs is VC friendly nonetheless.</p>

<p>I am going to state some problems of Emacs when buiding with M$VC, which
I tried several times, and then elaborate upon the process of successfully
building it with MinGW tools.</p>

<h1>Emacs developers ignore the M$VC toolchain</h1>

<p>Many open source projects, such as Python and VIM, are compiled with Visual
C++ compilers on Windows. M$VC is indeed a litter better for native Win32
programs than MinGW port of GCC: it produces smaller executables and may use
more windows specific optimisations. Emacs, however, though with support for
VC toolchains, has never been successfully compiled by me with msvc. And guess
what, a small syntax error in nmake Makefile is still in the official release,
making a scaring error message when you run nmake, which means that they never
tried even once building Emacs with the VC toolchain!</p>

<p>And another problem is that, the Emacs garbage collector seems to have
problems when compiled with VC, and this problem has previously shown on
Mac. It is compiler specific. After you have a temacs executable, in the
dumping process, an <code>Invalid function: "DEAD"</code> error message shows when temacs
is loading elisp files. So the closest point I have reached in succeeding in
compiling Emacs with VC is getting a temacs executable.</p>

<h1>Compiling with MinGW</h1>

<h2>What is needed:</h2>

<ol>
<li>MinGW C Compiler</li>
<li><code>cp</code> and <code>rm</code> from gnuwin32 <code>coreutils</code> (to handle special directory names
with the unix convention used in makefiles, and I think <code>del</code> and <code>copy</code> is
better if converting all these unix dir names to windows)</li>
<li><code>makeinfo</code> from MSYS, because gnuwin32 version will break when compiling
the large Emacs Manual. If you are ok without manuals, this is not needed. (I
guess a elisp version of this program will be very good, as temacs can be used
to generate these info files)</li>
</ol>


<h2>Notice:</h2>

<ol>
<li>Do NOT use MSYS bash shell, or <code>cp</code> and <code>rm</code> from MSYS (as recommended
by the Emacs nt install instructions)</li>
<li>Use the cmd.exe shell</li>
</ol>


<p>I decieded not to include any external libraries (Emacs can use some external
libraries to show images), thus minimizes the requirements and complexity of
compiling.</p>

<h2>Now the process:</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Open cmd, add the required bin directories to your path</p>

<pre><code> set path=%path%;%gnuwin32root%\bin;%mingwroot%\bin;%msysroot%\bin
</code></pre></li>
<li>cd to the Emacs source root, and then cd to <code>nt</code> sub directory</li>
<li><code>configure --help</code> to read options, as you may need feed all <code>--without-*</code>
options to <code>configure</code></li>
<li><code>configure --with-gcc --no-debug --without-*</code></li>
<li><code>make</code></li>
<li><code>make info</code> if you want info manuals</li>
<li><code>make install</code> if you want related programs to be grouped together, and add
Emacs to <code>Start Menu</code> and registry (typically I don&rsquo;t want this)</li>
</ol>


<p>Note that I do not add <code>--prefix</code> option to the <code>configure</code> script, the
default is installing Emacs to the same directory as the source code. You just
need to copy the bin and related files to a new folder, then you are
done. <code>addpm.exe</code> adds in the registry a bunch of values concerning the
locations of Emacs intallation, which is not needed. So I usually do not run
<code>addpm.exe</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Funny Bug in Quantum Espresso]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/12/07/a-funny-bug-in-quantum-espresso/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-07T22:11:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/12/07/a-funny-bug-in-quantum-espresso</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I am running metadynamics simulations on MgSiO3 Perovkite with
Quantum Espresso + PLUMED. However, the MD part of the PWscf code in QE is
rather unstable (compared to some non-free alternatives, such as VASP). I
encountered many problems using QE and PLUMED, and the bug discussed in this
post made me suffer a lot.</p>

<p>I think the this combination (PW + metadynamics with PLUMED) is rarely used by
people, since I found a bug that appears again and again, and no one complains
about it. This bug exists in 4.3.2 and the latest 5.0.1 version.</p>

<p>When I start a MD run with the PLUMED plugin enabled, most of the time, the
code fails, reporting a message:</p>

<blockquote><pre><code>  from randy : error #      1038
  j out of range
</code></pre></blockquote>

<p>before entering the MD loop.</p>

<p>I sought through the source code, and found that this error is reported by the
random number generator of QE. If the random number generator, which is so
fundamental and frequently used by the code, is buggy, then why does not
anyone experienced this bug before? Actually, when I first reported this bug
to the maintainer of the code, he was doubting the possibility of the bug.</p>

<p>After studying the code for a while, I finally figured out why the bug
happened.</p>

<p>In function <code>randy</code>, it first processes the seed as <code>idum</code> using:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>random_numbers.f90 line 53</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='fortran'><span class='line'><span class="nv">idum</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">MOD</span><span class="p">(</span> <span class="nv">ic</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nv">idum</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nv">m</span> <span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The maintainer does not remember who wrote this code, and the reason why. It
indeed causes problems if the seed is larger than ic (which is a fixed
parameter).</p>

<p>I  think this is the source of generating many negetive numbers. The random
seed must be too large. Where is the seed generated?</p>

<p>I found that <code>set_random_seed</code> uses current time components to generate a
seed:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>random_numbers.f90 lines 83-85</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='fortran'><span class='line'><span class="c">! itime contains: year, month, day, time difference in minutes, hours,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">!                 minutes, seconds and milliseconds.</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">iseed</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nb">itime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">8</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nb">itime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">6</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="nb">itime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">7</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nb">itime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Here in China we have <code>itime(4)</code> as 480 (timezone UTC+8), which is a constant
for any particular region, whereas in Europe <code>itime(4)</code> is much smaller. And
quite likely <code>iseed</code> will be larger than the <code>ic =150889</code> in China. So
depending on the value of <code>itime(8)</code> in milliseconds, which changes rapidly
and may be a large number, in China we got large seed, thus negative random
numbers.</p>

<p>If I remove the <code>itime(4)</code> in <code>set_random_seed</code>, PWscf never crashes with or
without <code>-plumed</code>. I believe this correction has no problem since it is what a
British user (UTC time, with itime(4) = 0) would get.</p>

<p>The maintainer corrected the buggy <code>randy</code> code. The problem seems to be
solved. However, I still do not understand the problem completely. Why the
error is always 1038, as the seed should be random? Why without <code>-plumed</code>,
does this apparent error not show? This is rather confusing, yet I do not have
the time and knowledge to dig into it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quantum Espresso及PLUMED安装指南]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/11/08/quantum-espresso-and-plumed-installation-tutorial/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-08T21:23:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/11/08/quantum-espresso-and-plumed-installation-tutorial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quantum Espresso（以下简称QE）和PLUMED结合，能做很多有用的模拟，尤其是
Metadynamics这种高级动力学。但是Quantum Espresso的安装程序有一些问题，
在我们模拟实验室的Earth和Venus上安装，不能正确识别LAPACK、ScaLAPACK和
FFTW库，需要手工更改make.sys，才能产生比较高效的程序。PLUMED的安装比较
容易，但是各种材料上说法不一，这里我讲最直接和简单的办法，希望对各位有
帮助。</p>

<h2>1. 获得安装包</h2>

<p>目前PLUMED最新版是1.3，支持QE的4.3.2版本，是4系列的最新版。但QE目前的
最新版是5.0.1，还没有广泛使用。我们可以同时安装这两个版本。请各位到官网
上下载具体的源码包。</p>

<h2>2. 解压到目录</h2>

<p>QE的安装没有Install的环节，也就是源码和程序都在一个目录里面，因此我们直
接把源码包解压到安装的位置。PLUMED只是作为插件存在，不需要单独安装，但
是为了方便，我也把它解压到一个安装目录。例如Earth上安装目录分别为：</p>

<pre><code>/public/software/QE/espresso-5.0.1/
/public/software/QE/espresso-4.3.2/
/public/software/PLUMED/plumed-1.3/
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[C#反射教程]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/11/06/csharp-reflection-tutorial/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T17:14:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/11/06/csharp-reflection-tutorial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>什么是反射？</h2>

<p>反射（reflection）在英语里有自我内省的意思，即是查看自己的内在。</p>

<p>在编程语言中，反射是指程序可以动态获得自己本身信息。我说的程序本身的信
息，是指诸如一个函数的字符串名字和参数、返回值类型，一个类的名字，类的
方法、字段、属性、事件等等。这些在程序设计时都是容易知道的，但是程序在
编译完成并执行时，这些信息都不同程度地丢失了。例如C语言，函数的编译通常
只保留一个函数的名字在最后的binary的符号表中，想要获得这个函数除了名字
以外的信息是很困难的（有时候甚至可以strip掉所有的符号信息，只保留函数的
入口地址，这样什么都没有了）。</p>

<p>这些信息被称为Metadata（元数据），有些人称作数据的数据。听起来有些装B，
其实就是编译型语言把源码中有关程序自身的信息存储到目标文件里，而不是抛
弃掉，就叫做元数据了。</p>

<p>但是实际上，反射这种东西很早就存在了。例如：</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Windows编程中，GetProcAddress可以根据一个DLL中函数的名字来获得其实际
地址，从而动态调用这个函数，而不用事先就在程序中显式调用。这提供了很大
的灵活性，COM的一个重要基础就是能够动态加载DLL并通过这种方式调用函数。
Linux系统动态链接库也有类似的功能（dlopen，dlsym）。</p></li>
<li><p>解释语言一般都有很强的反射能力，因为解释语言直接从源码执行，也不会丢
失任何有关源码的信息。Lisp中，程序的代码和数据没有区别，因此本质上可以
获得所有代码的信息，也可以动态执行任何一段在运行时构建的代码。
JavaScript的对象即是关联数组，所有的Field都可以用字符串来存取，Python有
getattr和setattr函数。</p></li>
<li><p>一般使用反射对程序效率有较大的负面影响，解释型语言在机器的计算能力还
不强的时候根本得不到流行，这是很大的一个原因。但是现在计算能力空前强大，
所以即使有些影响，对于一般的应用都问题不大，但是反射的灵活性和对很多问
题的优雅解决（使得程序的设计更加模块化，可以动态加载可执行代码等），促
使这类技术逐渐流行起来。</p></li>
</ul>


]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[被误解的Tcl]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/11/06/tcl-the-misunderstood-chinese-version/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T14:45:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/11/06/tcl-the-misunderstood-chinese-version</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>原文见<a href="http://oldblog.antirez.com/articoli/tclmisunderstood.html">http://oldblog.antirez.com/articoli/tclmisunderstood.html</a>，版
权归原文作者所有；译文 &copy; 2012 Derek Li。本文原始翻译时间是
2012-2-12日，后来我的空间到期，不打算更新，所以转到现在的博客上。</p></blockquote>

<p>最近有一篇链接自reddit的题为
<a href="http://www.cabochon.com/~stevey/blog-rants/tour-de-babel.html">Tour de Babel</a>
的文章，如果你读的话就会发现这篇文章说（除了一堆其他的胡言乱语）：靠，
Python在能想象到的各方面都比Tcl好得多了，但人们还用Tcl来当作嵌入式解释
器。</p>

<p>好吧，整篇文章是有点……不是那么回事。但是不幸的是，虽然很多错误观念很
快被知情的读者发觉了，但是这个反对Tcl的观念却被认为是理所当然的。我希望
这篇文章能说服人们，Tcl还没有那么不堪。</p>

<h2>开场白</h2>

<p>在我的编程生涯里，我使用了很多语言去写不同的应用：用C语言写了很多免费/
付费的程序，用Scheme写了一个Web CMS（内容管理系统），用Tcl写了几个网络
/Web应用，用Python写了一个商店管理程序，等等。我也玩过不少其他的编程语
言，例如Smalltalk，Self，FORTH，Ruby，Joy……然而，我从不怀疑，<em>没有哪
门语言像Tcl一样被误解得如此之深</em>。</p>

<p>Tcl不是完美无瑕，但大多数的不足并不是在语言设计本身，而是Tcl“之
父”（John Ousterhout）几年前去世了，连同他那种可以做出强势决定的专一的
领导力。只要做出正确的改变，克服Tcl的大多数不足并保留其强大功能是可以的。
如果你不相信Tcl异常强大，请先<em>花点时间</em>来阅读这篇文章。可能你读完之后还
是不喜欢它，但希望你尊敬它，同时你将有足够强大的论据来反对这种“Tcl是玩
具语言”的误解。这种误解如此小气，比“Lisp括号太多”更甚。</p>

<p>在我们开始之前，我先花点时间解释一下Tcl的工作原理。Tcl像世界上其他优秀
的语言一样，拥有一些概念，这些概念组合起来，能够实现编程自由和充分的表
达力。</p>

<p>在这个简短的介绍之后，你会了解在Tcl中，怎样使用普通过程（procedure）实
现像Lisp一样的宏（macro）（比Ruby的Block强大得多），怎样重定义语言本身
的几乎所有方面，怎样在编程时忽略类型。Tcl社区开发了数个OOP系统，大规模
的语言重定义，宏系统，和很多其他有趣的东西，仅仅使用Tcl本身。如果你喜欢
可编程的编程语言，我打赌，你肯定至少饶有兴趣地看一眼Tcl。</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Modify Keyboard Layouts Easily in Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/10/26/how-to-modify-keyboard-layout-in-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-26T23:20:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/10/26/how-to-modify-keyboard-layout-in-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you want to remap the CAPSLOCK key to the Control key or something else,
you will find many tutorials on the internet (most of them are of course for
Emacs learners). However, quite a few of them are outdated and unnecessarily
complicated (for me). In a modern version of Ubuntu, you can accomplish this
easily in the system settings dialog. I believe Ubuntu learned this from Mac.</p>

<p>Here is how (12.04 LTS):</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress: A HARD Way to Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/03/31/octopress-a-hard-way-to-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-31T19:33:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://dingmaotu.com/blog/2012/03/31/octopress-a-hard-way-to-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>From Ruby Installation to AN Octopress Blog</h2>

<p>It needs quite a lot effort to setup an octopress blog. First of all, trying to use ruby under Windows is just painful, so I use CentOS to do all these (in a VMWare Player Virtual Machine). I downloaded RVM, following the RVM homepage guides, and did not succeed for several times. That was because I omitted the &ldquo;requirement&rdquo; step (I thought RVM will install requirements for me). However, I did build ruby successfully and was happy, until I had found that gem, heroku were not functional. I had to install zlib, openssl etc. with RVM. But in China you cannot even access zlib homepage (similarly ruby-installer, vimeo, facebook, you name it). I then remembered the &ldquo;requirements&rdquo; step, and just yum-ed them all.</p>

<p>I have learned a bit Ruby, so octopress setup guide is relatively easy to understand. The setup is OK now, this blog being the first to test Octopress functionality, markdown syntax, and code rendering.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
